<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Time Series Analysis | jorge de la cal medina</title>
    <link>https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/tag/time-series-analysis/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/tag/time-series-analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Time Series Analysis</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/media/icon_hu4b3f6377c7303de9b28b0102381835f4_3695020_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Time Series Analysis</title>
      <link>https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/tag/time-series-analysis/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collective Mood-States and Investment Behaviour during a Global Pandemic</title>
      <link>https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/project/collective-mood-states-and-investment-behaviour-during-a-global-pandemic/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jorgedelacalmedina.github.io/project/collective-mood-states-and-investment-behaviour-during-a-global-pandemic/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we want to investigate whether collective mood, triggered by a real event, has some influence on stock prices considering a causal structure that determines the mechanisms by which collective mood affects stock prices. We take the 2019-2020 coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) pandemic to be an appropriate example of a real event that influences stock prices directly and causes a change in collective mood. The pandemic affects the world economy and has high media coverage; we assume thus an impact on stock markets. It represents an exogenous variation in the set of beliefs individuals have about the world but also affects their emotional states significantly (which allows us to investigate the role emotional states play in investment behaviour in the first place). To measure the variation in collective mood states, we develop a tailor-made sentiment analysis tool classifying tweets into positive/negative, active/passive and weak/strong to build a time series reflecting average Twitter sentiment over time. We perform on the resulting sentiment time series a Vector Autoregression (VAR) analysis by regressing the Standard &amp;amp; Poor’s (SP) 500 and Dow Jones Industrial Average (DJI) index to our sentiment time series. Subsequently, by conducting Granger causality tests followed by a Johansen co-integration test, we investigate whether our sentiment categories have an effect on stock prices.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
